Guide to the Sarah Christianson photographs, 2012-2015 RL.11088
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Sarah Christianson photographs
2012-2015
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Christianson, Sarah, 1982-
Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
RL.11088
1.0 Linear Feet 1 flat box 30 11x14 inch Type-C limited edition photographic prints on Kodak Endura paper made directly from 120 and 4x5 color negatives.
1.2 Gigabytes 1 optical disc containing 30 digital images in TIFF format.
Sarah Christianson is a photographer originally from North Dakota. This portfolio of 30 11x14 inch color chromogenic prints is from her project, "When the Landscape is Quiet Again: North Dakota's Oil Boom," which won the 2015 Archives of Documentary Art Award for Women Documentarians. Since 2012, Christianson has been documenting through her photographs the legacy of oil booms and busts in North Dakota and how the region's agrarian landscape and environment is changing again today, due to horizontal drilling and hydraulic fracturing. Acquired by the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Biographical Note
Sarah Christianson (b. 1982) grew up on a four-generation family farm in the heart of eastern North Dakota's Red River Valley (an hour north of Fargo). Immersed in that vast expanse of the Great Plains, she developed a strong affinity for its landscape. This deep-rooted connection to place has had a profound effect on her work: despite moving to San Francisco in 2009, she continues to document the subtleties and nuances of the Midwestern landscape and experience through long-term projects.
Christianson earned an MFA in photography from the University of Minnesota. Her work has been exhibited internationally and featured by Mother Jones, High Country News, and PDN. She has received project grants from the San Francisco Arts Commission and the Center for Cultural Innovation. Her first book, Homeplace (Daylight Books), documents the history and uncertain future of her family's farm by interweaving her images with old snapshots and documents culled from her personal archive. Throughout her work, she uses her personal experiences and connection to the land to evoke a strong sense of place, history, and time.
The project "When the Land is Quiet Again" was funded by an Individual Artist Commission grant of the San Francisco Arts Commission and an Investing in Artists grant from the Center for Cultural Innovation. Additional support was provided by RayKo Photo Center and in-the-field assistance was given by the Dakota Resource Council, the Killdeer Mountain Alliance, the Northwest Landowners Association, and numerous other individuals.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Electronic records in this collection have been migrated to a library server and digital use copies can only be accessed onsite in the Rubenstein Library Reading Room.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Sarah Christianson photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2015.
Collection Overview
The Sarah Christianson photography portfolio When the Landscape is Quiet Again: North Dakota's Oil Boom, won the 2015 Archive of Documentary Arts Award for Women Documentarians. The collection contains 30 11x14 inch Type-C (chromogenic) limited edition color photographic prints on Kodak Endura paper made in the darkroom directly from 120mm and 4x5 inch color negatives, accompanied by one DVD with 30 digital TIFF files, from scans made directly from the negatives. Christianson provided the following abstract of her work:
"Since 2012, I have been documenting the legacy of oil booms and busts in my home state and how the region is changing again today, thanks to horizontal drilling and hydraulic fracturing. My photographs bear witness to the transformation of western North Dakota's quiet agrarian landscape into an industrial zone dotted with well sites, criss-crossed by pipelines, lit up by natural gas flares, and contaminated by oil and toxic saltwater spills. The oil fields are currently pumping out over a million barrels per day from 10,000 active wells, and companies are planning to drill thousands more."
"This project grew out of the internal conflict I felt over my family's involvement, the need to reconcile their role, and a responsibility to document these important events. Over the past three years, I have driven nearly 9,000 miles and flown for over eight hours in small Cessna planes across the length and breadth of the Williston Basin to create my images. I use traditional photographic processes because of the descriptive detail inherent in large-format negatives. I use a 4x5 view camera to consider the landscape in a slower, deeper manner. I craft my chromogenic prints in the darkroom because I enjoy the intimate, hands-on process of coaxing each image from the light and chemistry."
Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Hydraulic fracturing -- North Dakota; North Dakota -- Photographs; Chromogenic color prints; Color photographs; Digital images; Documentary photography -- North Dakota; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
- When the Landscape is Quiet Again: North Dakota's Oil Boom, 2012-2015; 30 items 1 flat box; Electronic materials consist of 30 TIFF digital images derived from an optical disc (RL11088-OP-0001), approximately 1.2 gigabytes.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Electronic records in this series have been migrated to a library server and digital use copies can only be accessed onsite in the Rubenstein Library Reading Room.
  - Flaring near the Blue Buttes, 2015 Jan. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Content
    Upwards of 30% of the state's natural gas is being flared. This is cheaper for companies to do, rather than building the infrastructure and pipelines needed to capture it.
  - Tioga Lateral Pipeline, White Earth River Valley, 2013 May. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Alliance Pipeline seized Brenda & Richard Jorgenson's "best land" through eminent domain and have failed to reclaim "the scar." Brenda says, "I don't need more stress. I don't need more reminders of the inadequacies of the companies that scarred this land. We have not received any compensation."
  - Corn field, Bottineau County, 2013 Sept.. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    "Caution: Hazardous chemicals may be present in this area. Failure to use caution may cause serious injury or illness!"
  - Gullickson Gravel Pit #1 near Cartwright, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gravel is in high demand because roads are in constant need of repair from heavy truck traffic.
  - The Skogens' bedroom window, 2013 May (Box 1, Folder 1)
    For oil wells drilled near homes, the current minimum setback distance is 500 feet. Many people are fighting to have this increased to be at least 1000 feet, but the North Dakota legislature has defeated all such proposals.
  - Flax from the Petersons' saltwater-damaged field, 2013 Sept. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Saltwater is an industry byproduct that can be up to 30 times saltier than the ocean. It burns the land, making healthy agricultural production impossible. The Petersons wondered, "Should we have to sacrifice our farmland to careless operators?"
  - Saltwater-damaged farmland, Antler, 2013 Sept. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    The Petersons' field has experienced several saltwater spills over the last few years. The brown and bare patches of land at the center show the extent of the spills and their sterilizing effects on the soil.
  - Keene First Lutheran Church, 2015 Jan. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Drilling rig near Little Missouri National Grasslands, 2013 May (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Killdeer Mountains, 2014 July (Box 1, Folder 1)
    This area is may things: a traditional hunting ground, a sacred Native American site for ceremony and prayer, a Civil war era battlefield where Dakota and Lakota families were massacred. It's also a place threatened by the development of mineral resources.
  - Well site carved out of bluffs near the Badlands, 2013 Aug. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    The Lakota called this area "mako sica" or "land bad." French-Canadian fur trappers did the same, claiming these were "bad lands to travel through" because of the rugged terrain. Although no drilling is taking place in Teddy Roosevelt National Park, the sights and sounds of oil development along its borders are clear.
  - Pickup abandoned in the Little Missouri National Grasslands, 2014 July (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Off-roaders launched this truck off a 100-foot cliff in the Grasslands, where vehicle use is restricted to established trails. A few months later, someone else blew up the vehicle with Tannerite, an explosive that is detonated by firing high-velocity bullets into it.
  - The Badlands south of Medora, 2014 July (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Aging infrastructure from the two prior boom-and-bust cycles can still be found across the state.
  - Natural gas flaring from my family's wells, Watford City, 2013 Aug. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - ECO-Pad well site on my family's mineral acres, Watford City, 2013 May. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    My maternal great-grandparents homesteaded near here in 1912. Although their farm was sold in the 1960s, my family retained the sub-surface mineral rights on the land. We have a share in 7 wells, with more on the way.
  - Man camp and frac sand depot, McKenzie County, 2014 July (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Continental Resources' Atlanta well pad, Williston, 2014 July (Box 1, Folder 2)
    This is the largest well pad in North Dakota to date, with 14 wells clustered together in the middle of Williston's new housing developments along the Missouri River.
  - Saltwater pipeline rupture, Antler, 2013 Sept. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    As the infrastructure from prior booms ages, an increasing number of spills are happening because of poorly maintained and monitored equipment. This 24-year-old pipeline ruptured when it became clogged with oil, causing saltwater to contaminate the surrounding farmland.
  - Barley from Artz's saltwater-damaged field, 2013 Sept. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    These samples of barley were collected on the same day, from the immediate area of the spill site (left) and from a more distant, unaffected patch of the field (right). The stunted growth of the heads on the left indicate that the saltwater spill had been going on for several weeks without detection.
  - Intermediate reclamation on new well sites, McKenzie County, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    After a new well is operational, companies may perform an intermediate reclamation: they reduce the overall size of the pad and return some of the surrounding land back to its former use.
  - Pipelines to Little Missouri Gas Plant, 2015 Jan. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Sweet Crude Travel Center, 2014 July (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Cheryl 14-23 1H, Zavanna LLC, 2012 Mar. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Oil waste pit near Cartwright, 2012 Mar. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Each well has a waste pit, which contains all the material removed from underground during the drilling process. The pits are lined with heavy plastics to prevent potential contaminants, such as benzene and arsenic, from migrating into the soil and groundwater. Once the well is finished, the pit is buried on site, amounting to thousands of small landfills across the state.
  - "We're on Our Way," Glenburn, 2012 Mar. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Well stake in teepee ring, Mountrail County, 2013 Sept. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    This stake marks the location of an incoming oil well, one of eight planned for this farmer's pasture. He had no say in their placement and is afraid to speak up for fear that his family's oil well-servicing business would be blacklisted.
  - LK-Wing Wells, near Killdeer Mountains, 2013 Aug. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    To minimize environmental impacts, oil companies are building "ECO-Pads," or groups of wells on a single site. These wells are adjacent to the Killdeer Mountains Wildlife Management Area, a haven for deer, elk, bighorn sheep, pheasant, grouse, wild turkey, and antelope.
  - One million gallons of saltwater spilled, Ft. Berthold Reservation, 2014 July. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    This toxic wastewater flowed downhill over two miles through a ravine to Bear Den Bay, part of Lake Sakakawea, leaving a swath of dead trees & vegetation in its wake. Officials do not believe the contamination reached the tribe's freshwater intake from the lake, but many residents in the area are skeptical of their claims.
  - Ft. Berthold Reservation near Skunk Bay, 2014 July. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Tioga Natural Gas Plant, 2013 Sept.. (Box 1, Folder 2)